<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Iero-metropolis, or, The holy, the great, the beloved new Jerusalem shortly to come down from God out of heaven : being the work of Gods own hands ... / by William Sherwin ...</title>
            <author>Sherwin, William, 1607-1687?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1670</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59935</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3405</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34224</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14151036</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14151036</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102111</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59935)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102111)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1070:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Iero-metropolis, or, The holy, the great, the beloved new Jerusalem shortly to come down from God out of heaven : being the work of Gods own hands ... / by William Sherwin ...</title>
                  <author>Sherwin, William, 1607-1687?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Francis Smith ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1670?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First word of title in Greek character.</note>
                  <note>"To the reader" dated: Jan. 17, 1669 &amp; 70.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Revelation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Second Advent.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102111:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102111:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ΙΕΡΟ-ΜΕΤΡΟΠΟΛΙΣ OR, The Holy, the Great, the Beloved <hi>NEW JERUSALEM, (a)</hi> Shortly to come down from God out of Heaven: <hi>b</hi> BEING The work of Gods own hands: <hi>(c)</hi> whoſe form will be perfectly cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cular in length, breadth, and height; equal 12000 furlongs: <hi>(d)</hi> having the glory of God, or light as a ſtone moſt precious, <hi>(e)</hi> prepared for the Lamb; Wife or raiſed Saints: <hi>(f)</hi> then to be made perfect in one; <hi>(g)</hi> there to behold Chriſts glory in his Davidical Kingdome <hi>(h)</hi> of the thouſand years reign with his Saints on Earth, <hi>(i)</hi> from Antichriſts laſt ruine, to Satans laſt looſing; <hi>(k)</hi> ſhortly then producing both the worlds deſtruction, and his own perpetual torment with all the damned in Hell. <hi>(l)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From Scripture evidence, abundantly made manifeſt, both by clear Texts and neceſſary Conſequence; more eſpecially compriſed in 15 well approved reaſons.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Sherwin,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel.</p>
            <p>See <hi>(a) Rev.</hi> 21.10. &amp; 20.9 <hi>(b) Rev.</hi> 21 2.10. <hi>(c) Heb.</hi> 11.10. <hi>(d) Rev.</hi> 21.16. <hi>(e) Rev.</hi> 21.11. <hi>(f) Rev.</hi> 19.7, 8, 9. com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with chap. 21.9.10. Heb. 11.16.40. <hi>(g) Jo.</hi> 17.21, 22, 23. <hi>(h) Jo.</hi> 17.24. Eſ. 9.7. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.32, 33. <hi>(i) Eze.</hi> 48. laſt, Rev 5.10. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4 <hi>(k)</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11. to the end, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.2.7. <hi>(l) Rev.</hi> 20.8, 9, 10.15. &amp;c.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Apoc. 3.21.</hi>
                  </bibl> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Eſa. 54 12, 13.</hi>
                  </bibl> I will make thy Windows of Agats, thy gates of Carbuncles, and thy borders of pleaſant ſtones: <hi>See Rev. 21.18, 19.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Ver. 13.</hi>
                  </bibl> And all thy Children ſhall be taught of the Lord, and great ſhall be the peace of thy Children, <hi>So Rev. 22.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Francis Smith,</hi> and are to be ſold at the <hi>Elephant</hi> and <hi>Caſtle,</hi> without <hi>Temple-Bar.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="outline">
            <pb facs="tcp:102111:2"/>
            <head>Scripture evidence for the New Jeruſalem on Earth to come.</head>
            <p>The Doctrine whereof is
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, proved.</item>
                  <item>Secondly, Improved.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Proved,
<list>
                  <item>Firſt, From the explaining and opening of the Text. <hi>Jer.</hi> 3. from <hi>ver.</hi> 14. to <hi>v.</hi> 20.</item>
                  <item>2ly. From many Propheſies and Deſcriptions thereof in the Old and New Teſtament; with Anſwers to ſome Objections; and 13. Reaſons ſet down, why it ſhall be on Earth, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3ly. From the Series and Order of things ſet down in <hi>Daniel,</hi> and explained more fully in the book of Revelation given to the beloved Apoſtle <hi>John.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>—Secondly improved.</p>
            <p>Firſt; for Redargution of the errours of ſeveral ſorts of perſons a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt theſe truths.</p>
            <p>Secondly; For Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition to three ſorts of men.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt; To ſuch as own theſe Divine Doctrines, to be mindful to improve them.</item>
               <item>2ly. To ſuch as really indeavour to improve them to be often mindful of, and much to be affected with the greatneſs of their mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and the greatneſs of engagement to duty thereby, if duly conſidered.</item>
               <item>3ly. To ſuch as own them not to beware of ſlghting ſo much Divine and ſacred Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture truth of ſo great weight and concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, both as to holineſs and happineſs, as many ſuch perſons little think of, or conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider; and moſt of all to take heed of op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing of them.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Thirdly; To exhort all men to make uſe of the light of their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding abilities, to ſearch into thoſe Scriptures that concern theſe things, that they may not be found fighters againſt any ſuch truth of God.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:102111:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VVHen the ancienter miſrepreſentations, about the time of the the riſing of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and ſome later pervertings are remove <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> from the Doctrine of Chriſts Kingdome upon earth in the thouſand years, <hi>Rev. 20.</hi> (as we ſhewed in our Preface to the <hi>Irenion</hi>) it will appear to be a Divine and Scriptual part of the glorious Goſpel of Chriſt, and to be nothing elſe but an explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſome Articles of the Chriſtian faith, according to holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; namely, how, and when Chriſt will come from the right hand of the Father to judg the quick and the dead at his next appearance, and his Kingdome, <hi>2 Tim 4.1.</hi> and in what order he will fulfill the bleſſed Reſurrection of the Juſt, <hi>Luk. 14.14</hi> or that firſt Reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Rev. 20.5</hi> in the ſaid thouſand years, with all thoſe great things to be accompliſhed according to Scripture, from his ſaid appearance, to the little ſpace wherein Satan ſhall be looſed afterwards; as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the final deſtruction of Antichriſt; the national and miraculous calling of the <hi>Jews;</hi> the Reſtitution of all things; the New Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and the New Earth; the reſtoring the Dominion over the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and their freedome from the bondage of Corruption, into the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious liberty of the Sons of God, <hi>Rom. 8.21.</hi> And in the ſaid firſt bleſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Reſurrection of the Juſt, the fulfilling of the prrmiſes to <hi>Abraham, Jſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> of the Promiſed Land, to them and their Seed for ever: The ſure mercies of <hi>David,</hi> how Chriſt ſhall rule on his Throne to the end of the world, <hi>Eſa. 9.7. 2 Sam. 7.16 25, 26.29.</hi> with many other excellent things belonging to that time, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not from Scripture be warrantably applyed to any other time (as we have ſhewed in a Treatiſe on <hi>Gen. 3.15.</hi>) then that wherein he will ſo eminently break the Serpents head; and this is that coming the ſecond time without ſin unto Salvation, <hi>Heb. 8.28</hi> At the firſt he came to ſatisfie for ſin; and by reaſon of ſin, all the time from thence to his ſecond coming, his Servants have been liable to ſufferings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as
<pb facs="tcp:102111:3"/> members of his myſtical body, with him, and for him, after his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample (though not without Sin) but then he will appear to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to them, to free them from ſuch ſufferings, by deſtroying their Enemies, and binding Satan; and powerfully enabling his Servants to ſerve him, <hi>Rev. 22.3.</hi> granting great and wonderful peace in the world to them, in thoſe times of refreſhing from his own preſence, <hi>Acts 3.19.</hi> redeeming the bodies of the faithful from the priſon and corruption of the Grave, and after the thouſand years, will ſave the Camp of the Saints, and the beloved City from the laſt attempt of <hi>Cog</hi> and <hi>Mag g,</hi> upon Satans ſeducement; and after Chriſts with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing in the time of that attempt, he will deſcend as ſaith the Apoſtle, with a ſhout, and the voyce of an Arch-angel, and with the Trump of God, <hi>1 Theſ. 4.17.</hi> though we know not whether he will be then out of the world in perſon, or at leaſt the raiſed Saints on earth, ſhall not even at that time have the Viſion of his glorious Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; but to the Creatures diſcovery he will then deſcend at the laſt general Reſurrection and Judgment, when Heaven and Earth ſhall flee away before his face, and no place be found for them, as ſaith St. <hi>John, Rev. 20.11.</hi> upon the fulfilling whereof, he will perfect the Salvation of all his people by carying his whole myſtical body with him into eternal bleſſedneſs in the higheſt Heavens; no more to withdraw from them, but that they ſhall ever thenceforth be with him the Lord, <hi>1 Theſ. 4.17.</hi> How then muſt he needs (from his ſaid ſecond coming, be glorified in his Saints, and be then admired by all them that believe, <hi>2 Theſ. 1.10.</hi> and how ought the faith of the ſaid things to chear and comfort their hearts againſt, and under all their ſufferings in the mean time, and make them with joyfulneſs to ſerve him, and praiſe him, and willingly even to ſuffer for him when he calls them to it, ſince he hath promiſed gratiouſly to be with them in the deepeſt waters of their afflictions, and will not ſuffer them to be tempted above their meaſure in the mean time, and will in the iſſue deliver <hi>Iſrael</hi> from all their afflictions, and even recompence their meaſure of faithfulneſs and ſufferings for him, with a ſuitable degree of glory with him, <hi>2 Tim. 2.12. Rev. 20.4.</hi> in that bleſſed New Jeruſalem ſtate upon earth, <hi>Eſa. 24.23.</hi> when the Lord of Hoſts will reign in mount <hi>Sion,</hi> and before his ancients gloriouſly; as from Divine Authority in the enſuing parcel, may be obſerved to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the great King, and the magnifying of Gods Divine wiſdom and goodneſs, and great conſolation to faithful Souls, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:102111:3"/>
            <p>A word or two I ſhall further add of the nature and uſe of my four parts lately publiſhed, which to ſome Chriſtians may prove advantagious: Firſt, the drift of the <hi>Irenicon</hi> is chiefly to prove that the things reſpecting Chriſts Kingdom upon Earth, were ſpoken of by all Gods holy Prophets ſince the world began, as the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> teacheth, <hi>Acts 3.21.</hi> with divers other heads of arguments to the ſame purpoſe; and an Appendex added to it concerning the bleſſed firſt Reſurrection of the Juſt: Yea, and all likewiſe that have written in the new Teſtament, have added ſome explications thereof, as in that ſecond book is manifeſt, but chiefly the great Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> in alm ſt all his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles;<note place="margin">Heb. 16. &amp; 2.5.6, 7, 8 &amp; 4 9 &amp; 9.28.10.13.37. &amp; 11.8 9, 10.13.14.16.22.35.39, 40. &amp; 12.22, 23 28.</note> but above all in that to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> as might be ſhew'd particularly in many Chapters thereof, as being the people moſt eſpecially concerned in things of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Unto which ſaid <hi>Irenicon</hi> was afterwards added this Parallel, or third part before intended, as pag. <hi>2d.</hi> of the former book, as a ſtrong founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that truth, both from <hi>Daniel</hi> and the Revelation of Jeſus Chriſt, which is only a Divine myſtical Expoſition (as we have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed therein) of that part of <hi>Daniel</hi> that was ſealed and ſhut up before, till the time of the end, or Goſpel times, as in ſome meaſure may be diſcerned by our ſhort ſummary of <hi>Daniel.</hi> As for the forerunner or firſt piece, it co ſiſts of divers things which were occaſional, and after placed together, as apparently very uſeful for the whole work; whereunto reference is afterward fitly made in the following parts: And for the fourth part, it contains many obſervations, and other par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars, very uſeful for the underſtanding of myſtical Propheſies, with the removal of prejudices from this Doctrine: And as from my own exerciſe by Gods gracious aſſiſtance in drawing up thoſe, I am by his goodneſs inabled to ſpeak groundedly and knowingly upon other ſubjects, reſpecting theſe things from Divine warrant; and eſpecially from the help of that golden Key of Chriſts Divine Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation, left to his Church for that purpoſe, to open that part of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels</hi> ſhut up Viſions; ſo may others alſo (by Gods bleſſing) by the help of thoſe parts, receive much advantage, which may be obſerved in the conſidering, both of the forementioned treatiſe on <hi>Gen. 3.15.</hi> of Chriſts breaking the Serpents head; Firſt Decreetively and Declaritively, before he began his Mediators Office joyntly with the Father, and with the Holy Ghoſt: And ſecondly, Executively
<pb facs="tcp:102111:4"/> in his Mediators offices, ever ſince the fall of ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hitherto; and will moſt eminently, as the great King, and only Potentate (as the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſtiles him) then do it in the <hi>Millennium,</hi> when (as he alſo ſaith, <hi>1 Cor. 15.25.) he muſt reign till he hath put all his Enemies under h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s feet;</hi> And ſo concerning the enſuing ſubject of the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which are as examples to ſhew the uſefulneſs of the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named books, as containing foundations thereof; wherein th re is often reference made to things contained in them which I wiſh all ſuch as l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve the glorious appearance of the great God and our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Jeſas Chriſt, ſeriouſly to conſider, and the great things thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to appertaining according to Scripture warrant; And chiefly to look to that direction at the end of the Parallel, <hi>pag 68.</hi> and well to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſe thoſe ſummaries of the Revelation in the forerunner <hi>pag. 22, 23. &amp;c.</hi> 
               <q>And in the <hi>Irenicon,</hi> pag. 26, 27, 28. with the Abridgment of <hi>Daniel,</hi> or the ſummary thereof hereunto annexed; for ſuch Abridgments help much in the diſcovery of the order of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rallel, to ſhew wherein the Revelation explains the Viſions of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel,</hi> which is a very ſtrong evidence of the truth, and gives great light to the underſtanding of theſe Divine Miſteries, from the hands of both thoſe beloved Meſſengers of God, the writers of them, which ſhould much commend theſe ſubjects to truly faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Souls; conveyed to them by ſuch high Favourites of the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I ſhall only here add this fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther direction in the uſe of the ſaid Books which I have often given already by word of mouth to divers knowing perſons; namely, to read the two laſt books firſt, and the References in them to the former: And ſo commending thee (Chriſtian Reader) to the guidance of the Spirit of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uth, to lead thee into all ſuch comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table and bleſſed truths of the Goſpel, as may make moſt for the glory of God and our Saviour Jeſus Ch iſt, and thy own great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing in the faith of ſuch great things pertaining to his glorious Kingdome on earth to come, for which end I am eſpecially</q>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in him</hi> William Sherwin.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102111:4"/>
            <head>Scripture evidenced for the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> on Earth.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Jerem. 3.17.</hi>
                  </bibl> At that time they ſhall call <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the Throne of the Lord; and all Nations ſhall be gathered to it, to the Name of the Lord, to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat firſt (on the negative part) this Text is not to to be underſtood of any <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that hath been deſtroyed, may be made evident from this por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Scripture, <hi>ver.</hi> 14. to 20. whereunto, and to the times whereof the things herein mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, are no ways competible: Firſt, not old <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi> call'd <hi>Sulem,</hi> in <hi>Melchiſedecks</hi> time, <hi>Gen.</hi> 14. after held by the <hi>Jebuſites</hi> in <hi>Joſhuaes</hi> time, and after ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued by <hi>David,</hi> and beautified and fortified by <hi>Solomon,</hi> the Type of the true Prince of Peace, (as that was alſo of the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that is to come) of which this Prophet and others fore-told the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation to come by the King of <hi>Babylon<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> neither was it of that after the 70 years Captivity, afterwards repaired and adorned by <hi>Herod;</hi> and as our Saviour denounced againſt it, laid even with the ground by <hi>Titus</hi> and <hi>Veſpatian,</hi> about 40 years after his death; for as that was leſs glorious in it ſelf, ſo it not only killed the Prophets, and ſtoned thoſe Servants of the Lord that were ſent unto it from God; but did not ſpare the Son himſelf when he came to gather her Children as an Hen gathers her Chickens under her wings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:102111:5"/>
            <p>But that by the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> here, to be called the Throne of the Lord, is meant, the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to come down from God out of Heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. may theſe three ways be abundantly confirmed: Firſt, from the due weighing of this Text and context. Secondly; from many Propheſies and Deſcriptions ſet down both in the Old and New Teſtament, which comport with this Propheſie, concerning the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> of which the Old was but a type: Thirdly, from the ſeries and order of the times of the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> ſet forth in holy Scriptures, which this portion of Scripture hath three times re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference unto, <hi>ver.</hi> 16, 17, 18. <hi>In thoſe days, at that time,</hi> &amp;c. which together with the context, contain many characters and marks to know that time from all others, and joyntly witneſs each to others; and becauſe the matter of the context doth ſo neceſſarily relate to the time of fulfilling in the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate, we ſhall conſider them here together: firſt, he ſaith in thoſe days, <hi>ver.</hi> 16. after he had before, <hi>ver.</hi> 14 ſet down what ſtate they ſhould then be in, namely, of Children, then beloved (as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of thoſe times, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.) for their Fathers ſake, and as appears in this Chapter, <hi>ver.</hi> 19. though they had backſlidden before, yet then returning at Gods call [<hi>Turn ye back ſliding Children,</hi> &amp;c.] Secondly; God there lays them down a reaſon reſpecting himſelf and an effectual motive in regard of them (then) <hi>for I am Married unto you, and that for ever in Truth, Righteouſneſs and Judgment,</hi> as the Prophet <hi>Hoſea</hi> further explains it, <hi>chap.</hi> 2.19. ſhewing how that people then ſhould call him <hi>Iſhi</hi> my Husband, <hi>ver.</hi> 16. this Marriage-ſtate of that people (then) with God and Chriſt, ſhould bring about the buſineſs; for this the Text is very punctual and evident in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to ſuch a ſtate of his people the Jews; and as he had made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient promiſes of ſuch mercy then to them, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. to 11. and <hi>Deut.</hi> 32. <hi>ver.</hi> 36. to 44. ſo he here declares he was, and would be mindful of them, and promiſeth to take them one of a City, and two of a Family, or (as a <hi>Rabbin</hi> reads it) two of a Countrey or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, and bring them to <hi>Sion:</hi> Again, he will do it when he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth, to give them paſtors after his own heart, <hi>ver.</hi> 13. <hi>to feed them with knowledg and underſtanding, ſuch as he foretold of</hi> (then) <hi>by</hi> Daniel, <hi>chap.</hi> 12.3. that ſhould be indeed wiſe to turn many to Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs of Juſtification, which belong in ſpecial to that time, as we may ſee afterward, and as <hi>Eſ.</hi> 62.6. <hi>her Watchmen ſhall never hold their peace,</hi> &amp;c. till he make <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a praiſe in the truth, where alſo much more of the like nature is obſervable.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:102111:5"/>
            <p>And though they ſhall be multiplyed and increaſed then, yet he ſhews <hi>ver.</hi> 16. they ſhall ſpeak no more of the Ark of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the Lord, for that was but ſymbolical and conditional, ſo that while the Ark was with them, the Lord might be abſent from them, as to his gracious preſence (as ſomtimes he was) and therefore ſaith, they ſhould not think or ſpeak any more of ſuch old Typical conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions as the Ark was; he minds them not only of his real, but per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal being with them, as their Meſſiah, in whom (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>Col.</hi> 2.9 <hi>the fulneſs of the Godhead dwelleth bodily.</hi> Shewing <hi>ver.</hi> 17. that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> then ſhould be his Throne; ſaying, at that time, they ſhall call <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> the Throne of the Lord, and all Nations ſhall be gathered to it, to the name of the Lord, (for h s name will then be great in the whole world) namely, when the Kingdoms of the world are become the Kingdoms of the Lord and of his Chriſt; not only by right (as they ever were) but alſo his (as they will be then) by their immediate uſe, and viſible poſſeſſion; and that the Nations might know (then) whither to repair to the name of the Lord, where his glory will then ſhine out eminently, he names the place again, ſaying to <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is further confirmed, <hi>ver.</hi> 18. by ſeveral other mercies belonging to the ſame time; firſt, the houſe of <hi>Judah</hi> ſhall walk with the houſe of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> thoſe two ſticks ſhall then be united to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether into one Kingdome, under one King to them both, as <hi>Exe.</hi> 3.7. and they ſhall both come together (then) <hi>out of the Land of the North,</hi> as this Prophet ſpeaketh again of the ſame time, <hi>chap.</hi> 16.15. &amp; 23.8. <hi>and they ſhall have that Land</hi> (then) <hi>given, as an Inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance unto their Fathers, as the days of Heaven upon Earth,</hi> as is Emphatically expreſſed, <hi>Deut,</hi> 11.21.</p>
            <p>Again, he declares how all this good ſhall be brought about, <hi>ver.</hi> 19. namely, <hi>Iſrael</hi> by vertue of their Adoption ſhall then have the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed poſſeſſion of the Nations, and of the pleaſant land; and as Children abide for ever in their Fathers houſe, for that Adoption will be unalterable, for thou (ſaith <hi>he) ſhalt call me Father, and ſhalt not turn away from me, for then their hearts ſhall be Circumciſed,</hi> as he alſo promiſeth, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30.</p>
            <p>So that then, as an Husband, he will be married inſeperably to that people, <hi>ver.</hi> 14. <hi>As a King he will ſet his Throne in the mid'ſt of them,</hi> ver. 17. <hi>as a Father he will give them the ſure Adoption, and therewith the large inheritance of the Hoſts of the Nations, and their own pleaſant land,</hi> ver. 19. which is further illuſtrated from their ready anſwer to his call <hi>[return you back-ſliding Children, and I will
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102111:6"/> heal your back-ſlidings]</hi> whereunto they make a willing and obedient Anſwer: <hi>Behold we come unto thee, for thou art the Lord thy God;</hi> and then proceeds to make a meek and gracious acknowledgment of their own, and their fore-Fathers ſin and unworthineſs; <hi>and that Salvation is only in and from the Lord,</hi> from v. 12 to the end of the Chapter. So that then will be ſupplyed to them Wiſdom and Grace, Preſervation and Bleſſing, Eminency and Security from the Lord, and Unity amongſt themſelves in the enjoyment of all good, conferred upon them, as is from this portion of Scripture very obſervable; which if duly conſidered, may evidently appear to be a large and ſtrong evidence of the happineſs of that ancient inheritance of God, the ſeed of <hi>Jacob,</hi> which they ſhall have in thoſe times upon Earth in the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>-ſtate, when it ſhall be the Throne of the Lord, and his Dominion ſo large in the world, that all Nations ſhall come thither to do him homage, or as it is otherwiſe expreſſed, <hi>Eſ.</hi> 2.2. <hi>All Nations ſhall flow unto it,</hi> yet not with deceitful Spirits, as men do ſome time, to great Conquerors or Monarches in the world; or after their own evil heart, as the <hi>Jews</hi> formerly, but as manifeſting themſelves to be the Sons of God by the Spirit of Adoption: So that by theſe many particulars from the context, it may appear, that the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſpoken of in the Text, is the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſpoken of, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. upon the national call and converſion of Gods ancient people the <hi>Jews,</hi> who ſhall then look upon him whom they have pierced, and with true penitence turn unto him, as <hi>Zac.</hi> 12.10. from which time they their Seed, and their Seeds Seed ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue the bleſſed of the Lord, <hi>Eſ.</hi> 61.9. &amp; 66.22. when that Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Jews</hi> ſhall be born in a day, and the Iniquity of their Land ſhall be taken away in one day, <hi>Eſ.</hi> 66.8. <hi>Zac.</hi> 3.9.</p>
            <p>The ſecond way of Confirmation, is from the many Propheſies and Deſcriptions, and Teſtimonies contained in the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, reſpecting the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> where firſt we may conſider thoſe eminent Texts, <hi>Eſ.</hi> 59.20, 21. when the Redeemer ſhall come to <hi>Zion,</hi> what a Covenant he then makes with her Children, and how ſhe ſhall ſhine when the glory of the Lord ſhall be riſen upon her, <hi>chap.</hi> 60. what acceſs there will be to her, and how ſtrangers ſhall build her Walls, and how Kings ſhall Miniſter to her, and her gates be continually open to receive the Forces of the Gentiles, <hi>&amp;c. ver.</hi> 9, 10.11. &amp; <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.24.26. and amongſt many other high ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions ſhe ſhall be called the City of the Lord, the <hi>Zion</hi> of the holy one of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and much of theſe Propheſies and ſuch as follow are applyed by Chriſt himſelf unto the ſaid New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> Rev.
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102111:6"/> 21, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and therefore are ſo to be underſtood; but to ſave tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribing more Propheſies under this head of proofs: ſee many more then we have toucht upon here, in our Prodromus in the letter of <hi>November,</hi> 3. 1663. <hi>pag.</hi> 18, 19, 20, 21. As for Scriptural deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> much is ſpoken by the Prophet <hi>Jeremiah</hi> and <hi>Eſay,</hi> and others, as we have in part already ſhewed; but eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially it is largely deſcribed by <hi>Ezekiel</hi> in his nine laſt Chapters, where he at laſt declares the name of the City to be <hi>Jehovah Sham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> the Lord is there; being probably in part, the ſame that is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed more gloriouſly by Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. for the uſe of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile Church, as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> had ſet it forth for the <hi>Jews</hi> before: ſee Obſervation third in our laſt part, <hi>pag.</hi> 18, 19.</p>
            <p>Again, in the New Teſtament our Saviour ſtiles it the City of the great King, <hi>Math.</hi> 5. and where the Tabernacle of God ſhall be with men, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. and Chriſt reign with his raiſed Saints a thouſand years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. and of which City, the Lamb will be the viſible light inſtead of Sun, Moon, or Candle; and where his Saints ſhall behold his glory which his Father hath given him, <hi>Jo.</hi> 17.24. It is that place which our Saviour told his Diſciples he went to prepare for them, <hi>Jo.</hi> 14.1. and that after his going from them, he would come again and receive them unto himſelf, that where then he will be, they might be there alſo, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. even in his Kingdom, aſſigned to him by his Father, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13, 14. at the time when <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> as in the the Text, ſhall be called the Throne of the Lord, as (by Gods aſſiſtance) we ſhall further manifeſt, at which time our Saviour alſo hath appointed a Kingdome to his Diſciples, <hi>Luc.</hi> 22.29, 30. even as his Father had appointed unto him, that they might not only eat and drink at his Table in his Kingdom, but ſit on Thrones, judging the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> which only can be in the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi>-ſtate, according to Scripture: It is that City whoſe maker and buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God is ſaid to be, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11 10 the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that was free, when the other was in bondage with her Children, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. which is the Mother of all the faithful, and which is to be above, till the time of its coming down from God out of Heaven, when Chriſt will bring all his Saints, and ſuch as ſleep in him, with him, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.14. and therefore it is deſcribed by the Apoſtle, to be the City prepared by God for the faithful fore-Fathers; yet ſo, as for all fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture believers likewiſe, that they without us (ſaith he) might not be made perfect, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.40. or perfect in one as the Lambs Wife (as the ſame Jeruſalem is called, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.9, 10.) whoſe priviledges are there deſcribed to be exceeding great; for there ſhall be no hunger,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102111:7"/> pain, crying, and all tears ſhall be wiped away, there ſhall be no more curſe, but the Throne of God, and the Lamb ſhall be in it: and therefore all Joy, Glory, and Happineſs ſuitable to that State, as <hi>Chap.</hi> 21. &amp; 22. to <hi>ver.</hi> 7. is largely and divinely (though My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteriouſly deſcribed) all which Prerogatives of that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>appy condition, are largely ſet forth both in Old and New Teſtament (as the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned Quotations, with many others) may abundantly Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, if they were particularly inſiſted upon for glorious things (ſaith the holy <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi>) are ſpoken of thee thou City of God, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 87. Which hath ſpecial reference unto thoſe times, when the Nations ſhall come unto her, as <hi>Egypt, Aſſirya,</hi> &amp;c. as <hi>Eſa.</hi> 19. from <hi>verſe</hi> 18. to the end: When alſo the freſh Springs of Divine Grace will flow from thence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As is alſo deſcribed in <hi>Ezekiels</hi> laſt Viſion.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But the new</hi> Jeruſalem, Rev. 21. <hi>is ſaid to come down from God out of Heaven, and to be a City; whoſe Maker and Builder God is ſaid to be,</hi> Heb. 11.10. <hi>which</hi> Abraham <hi>is ſaid there to have looked for: And is that City prepared for the faithful Fore-fathers (as was ſaid from</hi> verſ. 40.) <hi>But that in the Old Teſtament foretold, is to be Built by Men, and Strangers ſhall build the Walls of it, and Kings, and Nations bring their Wealth and Glory to it,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> In anſwer whereunto we are to conſider, that according to Scripture, the <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate at that time, will conſiſt of Saints in a twofold condition: Firſt, of the Nation of the <hi>Jews,</hi> with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Iſrael<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tes</hi> converted, and all other converted Nations that ſhall joyn themſelves to them, with their Kings all abiding in their Bodies and animal L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fe as formerly.</p>
            <p>Again, it will conſiſt of ſuch Saints, as Chriſt at his ſecond com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing brings with him, as <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.5. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. laſt. who ſhall have their Bodies raiſed in their order, as ſaith the Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.18. who will be another ſort of Inhabitants in that New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate, though in a much more bleſſed and holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.6. In which reſpect, the Scripture ſeems peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arly to aſcribe to God, the making and building of that City, as a Manſion fitted for the raiſed Saints, and a place of glory for them; then to behold Chriſts glory which then he will have in his Mediators Viſible Kingdom upon Earth, ſuitable to that eſtate, which City ſhall have Foundations, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10. But whether it ſhall be by theſe Foundations elevated on high above the Earth, or otherwiſe; and have Streets of Gold, like to tranſparent Glaſs, that the glory of it may be diſcerned in ſome meaſure by other Saints then in the world,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:102111:7"/> and is ſet forth by Chriſt to be ſquare and a perfect Cube the height, as much as the breadth, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th all the excellencies ſet down by him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. &amp; 22. It being myſterious, we may not be too curious to inquire, nor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſh to determine (though ſuch things are there ſpoken of) which are not on the other hand negligently to be overlookt, as ſpoken to mans capacity, yet this may be reſolved upon: That ſince ſuch perſons have then and there ſuch happineſs aſſigned to them. God will make it every way ſuitable to ſuch a condition: But yet unto this glorious and happy Manſion which God prepared for that time for the raiſed Saints (as he did wonderfully prepare a body for Chriſt when he became man) even to that glorious Manſion, the Scripture ſhews the Kings and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the earth ſhall bring their glory and honour, as <hi>Rev</hi> 21.24.26. probably not ſo much to add to it, as to ſhew their aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ction towards it, and the Owner of it: And ſuch help and comfort they may then bring, as may be uſeful to the Nations that are ſaved, walking in the Light of the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> being in their bodies al ve as before; to them it is probable there wi l be much good uſe made of ſuch bounty of Kings, and munficence of Princes, and others in thoſe times, and Chriſt the great King much honoured by their Oblations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Wherein it is probable the goodneſs of God may in ſuch ways appear eminently in thoſe times, according to his many Propheſies and Promiſes to ſuch purpoſes; and the ſame God that hath appointed an eternity of Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, hath likewiſe prepared a ſuitable happineſs in that ſtate, for all ſorts of his Saints, then, which experience will manifeſt, though we cannot in all things now be reſolved particularly: God hath prepared that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> now above, where are the ſpirits of juſt men made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and God will, or hath prepared that City for them and others de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted ſince, Chriſts firſt to his ſecond coming, which ſhall then come down from him out of Heaven; when their Bodies ſhall be reunited to their ſouls, to remain with Chriſt in happineſs in his Kingdom upon Earth, and after that to all Eternity in the higheſt Heavens.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Another Objection may ſeem to be taken from</hi> Ezek. 16.55, 56. &amp;c. <hi>When I bring again the Captivity of</hi> Sodom, <hi>and her Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and the Captivity of</hi> Samaria, <hi>and her Daughters, then will I bring again the Captivity of thy Captives in the midſt of thee; which may ſeem an utter rejection of that people,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> That this Text or any other of the like nature, is not to be underſtood of an utter final rejection of any of them, let them be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly conſidered: Firſt, not of <hi>Samaria,</hi> or the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> whoſe chief City it was: for that in the appointed time of Gods mercy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to them, ſhall be again received and owned by him, may from
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:102111:8"/> many Texts of Holy Scripture appear abundantly, for thoſe two Sticks of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> ſhall be again united into one Kingdom, as <hi>Ez k</hi> 37. Then will be fulfilled what the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> foretels, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. that then all <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be ſaved. And ſecondly, <hi>Sodom</hi> and her Daughters, as well as <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> Eſa. 19.25. when it will be ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed be</hi> Egypt <hi>my people, and</hi> Aſſyria <hi>the works of my Hands, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>mine Inheritance.</hi> Even <hi>Sodom</hi> it ſelf may then have a part in that general Mercy, at the great Reſtitution of all things (though for its foul-ſins, now a ſtinking Lake in the mean time) ſince then Mercy will be extended to all Nations, to ſee the ſalvation of the God of <hi>Iſrael, Eſa.</hi> 52.10. <hi>For all the ends of the earth ſhall ſee the ſalvation of our God:</hi> Therefore alſo <hi>Sodom</hi> and her Daughters, and appears here ſo to be underſtood, becauſe joyned with the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> (as before <hi>Egypt</hi> and <hi>Aſſyria</hi> were, <hi>Eſ.</hi> 19.25. to whom belong the Adoption, and the Covenant, and the promiſes, (as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.4. to which purpoſe alſo, read in this Chapter and conſider, <hi>ver.</hi> 53, 54 compared with, and explained by <hi>ver.</hi> 61.63. for as he ſpake of their return at the ſame time, ſo toward the end of the Chapt. upon the foundation of his own everlaſting Covenant, he would give them to her for Daughters, and at ſuch a time as not only ſhe ſhould be aſhamed for her former miſcarriage, but when he alſo would be pacified towards her for all ſhe had done, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And although no mercy was to be expected to the Land of <hi>Judea,</hi> or <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by their own Covenant which they had broken, as is ſhewed <hi>ver.</hi> 59. <hi>thou haſt deſpiſed the Oath in breaking the Covenant, wherefore God denies ſuch mercies to be upon that foundation,</hi> ver. 61. <hi>Not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>by thy Covenant,</hi> but even upon that takes occaſion to renew and confirm his own Covenant, and that his everlaſting Covenant for the comfort of the faithful then, and of all times after, to come in a glorious way of free grace, formerly ſet down in the days of her youth; and now again in this Chapt. repeated, and confirmed, as appears manifeſtly, <hi>ver.</hi> 60, 61. to the end of the Chapt. in many full and forceable expreſſions (if thoſe verſes be duly conſidered) wherein the mercy of God reſerved for them againſt thoſe times, is both largely diſplay'd, and ſtrongly confirm'd; which Covenant is yet alſo more fully explained and clearly diſtinguiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Prophet, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31 31, 32, 33, &amp;c. which likewiſe the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> applyed in a more ſpecial manner to that people in his Epiſtle to the <hi>Hebrews,</hi> (though not excluding others) <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. <hi>ver.</hi> 8, 9, 10 11. according to what he had told the Gentils as a miſtery (as be calls it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 11.25.26 27.) from the words of the Prophet, <hi>Eſ.</hi> 59.20. <hi>The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall come to</hi> Sion, <hi>and to them that turn from tranſgreſſion in</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:102111:8"/> Jacob; a like confirmation hereof we have again from the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel</hi> largely ſet down, <hi>chap.</hi> 20.37.40, 41, 42, 43, 44 <hi>&amp;c.</hi> let all theſe Texts be ſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ouſly conſidered to this pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>poſe, wherein the riches of Gods free grace to that his ancient people, after all their ſo great and ſo long wanderings from him are ſo largely diſplayed.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But is not that which you call the New</hi> Jeruſalem <hi>upon Earth, to be meant of the higheſt Heavens?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is true that many have ſo underſtood it; but again, many oth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs that have taken pains in ſearching the intent of that and othet myſtical portions of Scripture, have been, and are of a different judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and that for many good and we ghty reaſons, as theſe following, and the like.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Becauſe the laſt part of <hi>St. Iohns</hi> Propheſie, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.26. is ſaid to be of things ſhortly to come to paſs; namely, in their due order in the world, and nothing by him there ſeen in Viſion, to be extended further then the worlds end, when the meaſure of ſhort or long time will utterly ceaſe <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The laſt Table of the laſt times, contained in <hi>chap.</hi> 20. leads us to the end of the thouſand years, and the finiſhing of the laſt Judgment, of which the 2 following Chap. are an explication, as is uſual in that book; firſt, to ſet down things more generally, and then more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly to explain them; as alſo is obſervable from that former Table of the times, <hi>chap.</hi> 11. which alſo reacheth to the ſtate of things on earth in the thouſand years.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>St. John</hi> ſaw that holy City, the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> deſcending out of Heaven from God, not aſcending thither, or being there.</p>
            <p n="4">4. When that general great rejoycing was at the deſtruction of the Enemies, <hi>chap.</hi> 19. to <hi>ver.</hi> 9 for theſe 2 reaſons; firſt, that the Lord God Omnipotent (then) Reigned. 2ly. That the Marriage of the Lamb then was come, and that his Wife had made her ſelf ready (which is af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards manifeſt to be above a thouſand years before the laſt Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection) and this Wife of the Lamb, is after explained to be the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> that <hi>St. Iohn</hi> ſaw deſcending out of Heaven from God, there called the Bride, the Lambs Wife, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.9. conſiſting of the bleſſed Saints then to inhabit it bodily in their order at the firſt Reſurrection, which is alſo in the following part of that chapt. ſo gloriouſly decypher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and in Chap. 22. to v. 6. therefore it is thence evident, that the ſaid <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Lambs Wife, deſcended above a thouſand years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the laſt Reſurrection and Judgment, and therefore all that time not to be in Heaven; moreover it is ſaid to be beſieged by <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> at the end of the thouſand years, as follows in the next reaſon.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:102111:9"/>5. The ſame holy City is ſaid to be compaſſed about by <hi>Gog</hi> and <hi>Magog</hi> at the end of the thouſand years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.9. which could not be done if it was not then in the world; and therefore the Viſion there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, when it firſt deſcended, which the Angel that had one of the 7 Vials then ſhewed to <hi>St. Iohn,</hi> calling it the Bride, the Lambs Wife, and all the priviledges and excellencies thereof muſt needs belong to it whilſt it is in the world, &amp; all thoſe many excellent things concerning it, <hi>chap.</hi> 21, &amp; 22. to <hi>v.</hi> 6. muſt needs belong to the ſtate of Chriſts Church in thoſe times on Earth, (as after will further appear) all tending to ſet forth that one deſcription of that holy City ſeen in the ſame Viſion, which was before ſaid to be ſo encompaſſed with <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Magog,</hi> with its privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges and appurtenances as follow in both Chapters.</p>
            <p n="6">6. It will be in that time when the Nations of them that are ſaved ſhall walk in the light of the ſaid New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> which they will not do in the ſtate of Heavenly perfection, when no Nations will be in the world, but all Saints will be perfect in one, <hi>Jo.</hi> 17, 23. in ſoul and body, and the whole myſtical body of Chriſt ſhall be completed in the members of it, and all received into perfect glory and happineſs.</p>
            <p n="7">7. In the ſame verſe the Kings of the Earth are ſaid to bring their own glory and honour to it, and therefore it muſt be in the time where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they enjoy ſuch honour and glory upon Earth, <hi>ver.</hi> 26.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Thoſe Kings are there ſaid alſo to bring the glory and honour of the Nations unto it, in the ſame verſe; and therefore it muſt be in the time wherein ſuch Nations have ſuch Kings, and ſuch glory and honour to be brought unto it, and theſe alſo were foretold, <hi>Eſ.</hi> 60. in many eminent expreſſions in many perticulars.</p>
            <p n="9">9 It will be in a time meaſured by moneths, when the Nations will alſo need healing; and therefore the uſe of the leaves of the Tree of Life, in the ſtreet of the City that bears fruit every moneth, is ſaid to be for the healing of the Nations, <hi>chap.</hi> 22.2, and ſo before the end of the world <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="10">10. The Sun, Moon, and Candle, at the ſame time will be uſeful to other places in the world, when the Lambs ſupereminent light will ſo enlighten that holy City, that there will be no need of any other, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22 5. and <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.23. as was alſo foretold of the ſame times by the Prophet. <hi>Eſay, chap.</hi> 24.23. Then ſhall the Moon be confounded and the Sun aſhamed when the Lord of Hoſts ſhall Reign in Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> and in <hi>Jeruſalem<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> and before his Ancients gloriouſly. So alſo <hi>Eſ.</hi> 60.19. <hi>The Sun ſhall be no more thy light by day, neither for bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhall the Moon give light unto thee, but the Lord ſhall be unto thee an everlaſting light, and thy God thy glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="11">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:102111:9"/>11. Upon the coming down of this New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> the Tabernacle of God is ſaid to be with men, and he to dwell with them, and they ſhall be his people, and God himſelf ſhall be with them, and be their God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 3. and was ſaid before in <hi>c.</hi> 20.4. Chriſt ſhould reign with his raiſed Sts. 1000. years, and that on earth, (expreſly ſay the repreſentatives) exulting greatly in it, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10.</p>
            <p n="12">12. Some of the former and enſuing promiſes are applyed by the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God in this Book to the ſaid new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate, as that of the new Heavens and the new Earth, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.16. ſo applyed <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.5. and that the Kings and Nations of the earth ſhall bring their glory to it in that time, <hi>Iſa</hi> 60.11. and ſo applyed <hi>Rev.</hi> 21, 24 26, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="13">13. It is the place where the repreſentatives, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10. ſhall reign with Chriſt upon earth being that City that God prepared for the faithful Fore-Fathers, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. the laſt and all believers ſince their times to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the juſt; wherefore it ſeems to be of ſo great largeneſs as containing 12000. Furlongs, which ſome reckon 500. Leagues; and which is moſt wonderful (as our late Annotators obſerve) the height and length and breadth are equal as a perfect Cube: who alſo reckon the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, deſcribed by <hi>Ezek.</hi> to be ſo great, as containing in compaſs about it, 18000. meaſures, or 4500. on each ſquare, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 48.16.</p>
            <p n="14">14. The City that <hi>Abraham</hi> particularly looked for, is ſaid to have foundations, whoſe maker and builder is God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10. and ſuch is that that ſhall then come from God out of Heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. having 12 founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, <hi>v.</hi> 14. of which, the <hi>Pſalmist</hi> ſeems prophetically to ſpeak, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 87.1. his foundation is in the holy Mountain; and which <hi>Pſalm</hi> is in many places applicable to thoſe times of the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> to come: and theſe foundations may ſeem to difference it (then) from that which is now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove, where are the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. called alſo <hi>Paradiſe,</hi> and <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſom, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that when the Sts. come with Chriſt at the ſaid <hi>Jeruſalems</hi> coming down from God out of Heaven, that their bodies may be raiſed &amp; united to their Souls at the firſt bleſſed reſurrection; ſuch foundations may be ſuitable to their condition (then) having their bodies reunited to them, and to that eſtate of the Church in the world de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed in <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. Moreover, <hi>Abraham</hi> that looked for ſuch a City having foundations, is called by the Apoſtle the heir of the World, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.12. through the righteouſneſs of Faith: by which Faith, ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, he received <hi>Iſaac</hi> from the dead in a figure, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.19. and according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Apoſtle ſeems to apply the divine efficacie of his faith in ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblance to Gods raiſing up the dead and calling things that are not as though they were, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.7. and proceeds to illuſtrate the power of his faith, that neither the deadneſs of his own body, nor the deadneſs of <hi>Sarah's</hi> womb did hinder it, in believing that he ſhould have that promiſed Seed:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102111:10"/> and ſo of the promiſed inheritance, often ſworn by God to <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob; Abraham</hi> had not of it to ſet his foot on, <hi>Acts</hi> 7. and that promiſe was looked for a farr of by him and others, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13. and yet believed and embraced by them; yea many others ſet down af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards, which obtained a good report by faith; yet (ſaith the Apoſtle) obtained not the accompliſhment of the promiſe, <hi>v.</hi> 39, 40. God having provided ſome better thing for us, that they without us ſhould not be made perfect, to wit, at the ſaid Reſurrection from the dead; and in the ſaid City which <hi>Abraham</hi> looked for, which hath foundations, <hi>v.</hi> 10. and that City prepared by God himſelf for the reſt of the faithful, <hi>v.</hi> 16. and <hi>v.</hi> 40, all which ſeem to point out the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate on earth at Chriſts ſecond coming; with many other great things to be accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhed in thoſe times, as we have ſhewed more particularly in a Tract on <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. and in our 4th. Part, Obſer. 31. and well may that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition be called an heavenly Countrey, becauſe it will be of an heavenly nature, and in an excellent ſtate and condition; when there will be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed an heaven upon earth, when Chriſt will bind Satan, and ſeal him up in the bottomleſs Pit that he ſhall not deceive the Nations for that ſpace of a thouſand years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.3, 7. and many wicked men be deſtroyed from the earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18. and he will bring all his Saints aſleep in him (till then) with him, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4.14. and an innumerable company of Angels to attend upon him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97, and all creatures ſhall bow the knee, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2. to do him homage, which are now in heaven, or earth, or under the earth, whoſe name is above every name; which ſeems excellent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly decyphered before us, by his own ſpirit, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. after he had taken the book from the right hand of him that ſat upon the Throne to looſe the ſeals thereof: the fulfilling of the contents of which, will cauſe that wonderful praiſe by the 24 Elders, and 4 Beaſts, or living Wights, by Angels, and all Creatures, from <hi>v.</hi> 10. to the end; and yet of that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, ſaith one, it is called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Countrey where their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers dwelt, as in many Propheſies and Promiſes it is ſtiled, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And the things concerning that State, ſeem therefore to be ſo ſtrongly and often aſſerted by the Spirit of God, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.9. and 21.5. and 22.6. to ſhew, that though many would be backward to believe them, yet they ſhould be not certainly fulfilled in the world in due time.</p>
            <p n="15">15ly. It is ſaid to be meaſured (as we have elſewhere noted) and like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe many other Propheſies and Promiſes are applicable from the Old Teſtament to that ſaid New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> State, as the Spirit of Chriſt in reſpect of thoſe forenamed, hath directed; and which may more largely be obſerved in our Prodromus, <hi>Pag.</hi> 18, 19, 20, 21. in the letter of <hi>Nov.</hi> 3, 1663.</p>
            <p n="3">3ly. And ſo we come to the 3d. way of confirmation of the New <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> to come on earth, namely from the Series and Order of the time
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:102111:10"/> in Scripture aſſigned for the ſetting up thereof in the world, to wit, upon the deſtruction of the Beaſt at Chriſts 2d. coming; whom, ſaith the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, Chriſt will deſtroy with the appearance of his coming 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. unto which he alſo adjoyns his Kingdom, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. at his appearance (ſaith he) and his Kingdom. And to this purpoſe, it is very obſervable, that when God was about to deſtroy the O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> for the greatneſs of the wickedneſs prevailing in it; by the ſame Prophets whereby he denounced the deſtruction of the Old to the terrour of the wicked; by the ſame alſo, he foretold the ſetting up of the New for the comfort of the faithful; wherein they in due time ſhould have their ſhares, as <hi>Eſ.</hi> 29.19. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.31, 32, <hi>&amp;c. Ezek.</hi> 37. and theſe do not only ſpeak of the deliverance of the <hi>Jews</hi> from <hi>Babylon</hi> after 70. years, but of the great reſtauration of all <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> which they ſet forth with many pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Marks and Characters belonging to it, as we obſerved from this Text, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.17. and from <hi>Eſ.</hi> 60. and many other places. But the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> in <hi>c.</hi> 37. of his Propheſie, doth not only deſcribe their deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verance to be wonderful, like a raiſing of dry bones from the Grave, and making them ſtand up in a great Army; but alſo largely there alſo ſhews the uniting both Kingdoms of <hi>Iſrael</hi> and <hi>Judah,</hi> into one, under Chriſt the Great <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> called there <hi>David,</hi> of whoſe Seed he was, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the fleſh, and in whoſe Throne he is to ſit ſo long as the Sun and Moon endure, from the time of the raiſing up the Tabernacle of <hi>David</hi> that was fallen, <hi>Acts</hi> 15, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yea, this 37 of <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> ſeems with the remainder of that book to the end, to be as a comment or expoſition of the main drift of divers of <hi>Daniels</hi> Viſions reſpecting the latter times: for as he by Viſions (as we ſaid) ſet forth how wonderfully God would raiſe and reſtore them, <hi>c.</hi> 37. ſo in the two next chapters, he largely by Propheſie fore-tells the ſtupendious deſtruction of their Potent Enemy <hi>Gog</hi> and his Multitudes, with <hi>Magog,</hi> which he ſpecially declares twice, ſhall be in the latter dayes, <hi>c.</hi> 38. <hi>v.</hi> 8. and <hi>v.</hi> 16. with many expreſſions agreeing to their great Enemy the <hi>Turk;</hi> and thereby God undertakes for the comfort of the faithful, to remove him which is to be the great hinderer of their freedome. And from thence in 9 chapters to the end, he ſets down his large Viſion of the New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and in the end de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares the name thereof ſhall be <hi>Jehovah Shamma,</hi> the Lord is there; which is alſo by Scripture order to be ſet up when the Enemies are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, as <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.45. and <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.2, 3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But <hi>Daniel</hi> in a more ſpecial way of Mercy from God to his faithful people from his time, had for their more abundant conſolation, in divers Viſions ſet down in order, the times to paſs over the <hi>Jews</hi> in their ſaid Diſperſions, and the ſeveral Oppreſſors of them in order to be deſtroyed, until their full deliverance come; and this both more generally in 4 wicked Monarchies before the fift came that ſhould deſtroy them, <hi>c.</hi> 2. by his interpretation of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buchadnezzars</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:102111:11"/> Dream which were again ſet before him in a Viſion of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> beaſts to ſubdue each other till the Son of mans coming in the clouds of heaven to receive his Kingdom over the whole world, upon the laſt beaſts deſtruction, <hi>Dan</hi> 7. and afterward in <hi>c.</hi> 8. &amp; in the end of the 9. &amp; in his laſt Viſion, <hi>c.</hi> 10, 11, 12. he hath things more particularly ſet down, reſpecting the 3 laſt Monarchies and Beaſt-like ſtates to the time of the ſtanding up of <hi>Michael</hi> the great Prince at the deſtruction of the <hi>Turk</hi> and the delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of <hi>Daniels</hi> people, <hi>c.</hi> 12. 1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as may more largely be obſerved from our Abridgement of <hi>Daniels</hi> Prophetical Viſions, and the Parallel of <hi>Daniels</hi> Viſions, with the Book of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> ſo far as reſpects the time of the end, or Goſpel times, from Chriſts firſt to his 2d coming; when the 4 Mettle-Kingdoms will be utterly and finally broken as the duſt in the Summer threſhing, and the wind drive them away: as <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.35. and the Date of the 4th beaſt be ended, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. when the Kings ſhall be Chriſts, and theirs to whom he hath appointed them, as <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.30. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the particularities to be accompliſhed in above 2000. years ſpace <hi>Daniel</hi> hath ſet down many things in ſuch order as ſeemed good to the ſpirit of God, to guide him and reveal any of them to him. But under the laſt Kingdom or Beaſt, <hi>Daniel</hi> hath many things ſhut up and ſealed until the time of the end (or Goſpel times) which Chriſt Jeſus the Lamb hath ſince in the book of the <hi>Revel.</hi> opened and explained in a wonderful divine manner; yea, and in great part fulfilled and accompliſhed likewiſe, which leads us to the end of <hi>Daniels</hi> Viſions when Chriſt ſhould appear and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel</hi> ſtand up in his lot at the end of the days. Which is the time the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is to have its being in the world, and all the Promiſes and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies concerning it, and Gods antient (people performed: and when it ſhall be called the Throne of the Lord, as from Chriſts own Revelation is ſufficiently manifeſt: and thus of the 3 ways of confirmation fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named at the beginning.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 1. Let us now proceed to ſome inprovement of this Truth by way of Application: And firſt, by way of Redargution or Reproof, it may hence appear how much they are to be blamed that think and ſpeak ſlightly of the great and national converſion of the <hi>Jews;</hi> and the happy eſtate of the <hi>Jews</hi> and <hi>Iſraelites</hi> united in one Kingdom, to be in the world in its ſeaſon, ſince Gods word doth ſo abundantly declare what wonderful mercie he hath ſtill in ſtore for them: But much more of ſuch as eſteem them finally little better than caſt-aways from Goſpel-grace, there is a vaile indeed upon the heart of that people, yet nevertheleſs that Vail (as ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.16) when they ſhall turn to the Lord, ſhall be taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way; ſo that the hope of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall not utterly fail or periſh: But leaſt of all will many believe that they ſhall have ſuch a glorious Church ſtate, as the word of God (as we have here, and elſe where ſhewed) as they with
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:102111:11"/> the <hi>Gentiles</hi> (when their fulneſs ſhall come in) ſhall enjoy together in the 1000. years reign of Chriſt upon earth: Let ſuch ſeriouſly conſider of it, how unchriſtian it is to recompence evil for evil unto them: The <hi>Jews</hi> ('tis true) in the Apoſtles time did indeed both deſpiſe and maligne the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and would not indure to hear of their receiving to mercie, but they were for the moſt part the obſtinate and unbelieving <hi>Jews,</hi> or at leaſt before God had wonderfully by word and viſion, by Miracles, and the Teſtimony of the ſpirit, put his owning of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> out of queſtion in the Church (then) before wich time the evidence of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> hopes was both obſcure and ſmall in compariſon of what the <hi>Jews</hi> have for the time to come, and that of ſtrong Scripture ground in Gods appointed time, when both <hi>Iews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> ſhall be joynt heirs of Gods enlarged grace to them both: And it ſeems very remarkable, that when the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of the firſt receiving of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> to mercy he quotes little Scripture for that purpoſe, and thoſe alſo which before were very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9.25, <hi>&amp;c:</hi> from, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 2.23. I will call them my people which were not my people, and her beloved which was not beloved: and from <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 1.10. in the place where it was ſaid, <hi>ye are not my people,</hi> there they ſhall be called the children of the living God: which had been difficult to have applyed to thoſe times, thoſe places, and perſons, had not God ſo powerfully and wonderfully confirmed and evidenced his good pleaſure there in thoſe reſpects. But when he comes in the ſame Epiſtle to ſpeak of Chriſt as the Miniſter of the Circumciſion, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.8, 9. and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the promiſes made unto the Fathers, whoſe poſterity the <hi>Iews</hi> were, and to whom the promiſes did belong, as he ſhews with many other pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, together with all the <hi>Iſraelites, Rom.</hi> 9.4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> he then heaps up many teſtimonies of the Prophets, and from <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the <hi>Pſalms,</hi> that ſhould all witneſs to the joynt happineſs of both <hi>Iews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> when all <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be ſaved: in reſpect of the former when our Saviour came the firſt time, be himſelf ſaid, <hi>Mat.</hi> 15.24. That he was not ſent in his own perſon, during the time of the Miniſtry, but to the loſt ſheep of the houſe of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> that was, only to the nation of the <hi>Iews,</hi> being the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Circumciſion as the Apoſtles phraſe is: But for the ſaid joynt grace to be aboundantly, gloriouſly, and wonderfully powered out on <hi>Iews</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> at the time of his 2d coming without ſin to Salvation, he applyes many pertinent places belonging to that time, ſeeming there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in in a ſpecial manner to be directed by the ſpirit of God to teach the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> (as <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. Apoſtle doth largely diſcover) that their greateſt mercy is then to be looked for, when the <hi>Iews</hi> ſhall obtain theirs, as by a reſurrection from the dead, when all <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall be ſaved, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with much more to ſuch purpoſes. And all thoſe texts which he names to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15.8, 9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> have ſpecial reſpect to the time of their uniting in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:102111:12"/> one ſheep fold one ſhepheard, as our Saviour himſelf hath like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe fore-told, <hi>Iohn</hi> 10.16. that there ſhould be one ſheep-fold and one ſhepheard: the 40th <hi>Pſalm</hi> is very prophetical of Chriſts wonderful pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valencie over his enemies then, above what was competible then to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> and <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.43. is the laſt part of <hi>Moſes</hi> prophetical ſong for po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity that ends with the union of <hi>Iſraelites</hi> and <hi>Gentiles:</hi> the 117th <hi>Pſal.</hi> is a ſhort and pithy propheſie and form of praiſe for that very cauſe: and <hi>Eſ.</hi> 11.10. with much of that <hi>c.</hi> (as both Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> and many others well obſerve) to be a glorious prediction of Chriſts ſaid Kingdom on earth, in that time of the uniting of <hi>Iſraelites</hi> and <hi>Gentiles</hi> in the grace of the goſpel to come as, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. before named; and the ſtate of the ſaid new <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> when his reſt ſhall be glorious, (as <hi>Eſa.</hi> 60.1. which by the context in <hi>Eſa</hi> 11. both before and after the 10. <hi>v.</hi> may aboundantly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear. But that which many ſuch men ſeek chiefly to avoid, is the yeilding of Chriſts <hi>Daviaical</hi> Kingdom here upon earth, the doctrine whereof (though in ſome parts of holy writ it be ſet down in a divinely myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call manner) yet the holy Scripture is plentiful for it, and very punctual for the time when it ſhall appear, and for many excellent and glorious things belonging to it, (if truly pious and dilgent ſearch thereof be made) as if that great Redeemer of his antient people beloved (as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith) for their Fathers ſake would not come in his time appointed, would not come to mount <hi>Sion</hi> to deliver them and others, even to all ſuch as ſhall turn away from tranſgreſſion in <hi>Iacob</hi> as is promiſed, <hi>Eſa</hi> 59.20. when they ſhall look upon him (when he appeareth) whom they have pierced, <hi>Zac.</hi> 12.10. and turn by true repentance to him from the iniquities of their fore fathers. And in both theſe reſpects great ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal is given to the <hi>Iews,</hi> for they know there is a ſtrong entail of many great both ſpiritual and temporal mercies to their faithful fore-fathers, and their poſteritie in thoſe times to come (though for a time their ſins withhold thoſe mercies from them) and that as they expect, though, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not in that manner, the ſon of <hi>David</hi> their Meſſiah will come to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver them the ſacred Scriptures give ſtrong aſſurance, and which time of their redemption ſeems to draw nigh as our Saviour teacheth, <hi>Lu.</hi> 21.28. and that the Kingdom of God is nigh at hand, <hi>v.</hi> 31. the ſignes whereof when they ſhall ſee, he bids them there lift up their heads: for then accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the prediction of the Angel to the bleſſed <hi>Virgin, Luke</hi> 1.23. the Lord ſhall give to Chriſt the Throne of his Father <hi>David,</hi> which is the ſame which our Saviour told his Diſciples his Father had, then, as <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13, 14. appointed unto him, even as he appointed unto them at the ſame time a Kingdom, even that Kingdom that they may eat and drink at his table in his ſaid Kingdom, and ſit upon Thrones judging the 12 Tribes of <hi>Iſrael, Luke</hi> 22.29, 30. which will be the only time for them to doe,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:102111:12"/> for afterward in heaven there will neither be ſuch eating or drinking, or judgeing or ruling over others or their cities, as <hi>Luke</hi> 19.17, 18. and it is to be obſerved thoſe texts of Scripture ſpeak of ſuch Kingdom as was to come, and therefore not to be underſtood of Chriſts ſpiritual Kingdom which he had both then, and in all the times of the old Teſtament, and as when <hi>Solomon,</hi> the type of Chriſt in that particular, ſat upon the Throne of <hi>David,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 2.12.24. it could not be ſaid he ſat upon his Throne ſpiritually, but perſonally in <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> ſo neither in this reſpect can it be ſaid, that Chriſt of the ſeed of <hi>David</hi> according to the fleſh ſhall then on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpiritually, but perſonally ſit upon the Throne of <hi>David</hi> in the new <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> which then [as in the text] ſhall be called the Throne of the Lord. Though he hath always as God had a ſpiritual Kingdom in the world; but the ſitting upon the Throne of <hi>David</hi> for the future belongs to him as man, as the fruit of <hi>Davids</hi> Loyns according to the fleſh, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.30. which the Apoſtle <hi>Peter v.</hi> 35. ſhews ſhould be, when God makes his Foes his foot-ſtoole; for as when Chriſt is frequently in the goſpel called the Son of <hi>David,</hi> we cannot in that ſenſe ſay he is the Son of God: ſo when he is ſaid to ſit on the Throne of <hi>David,</hi> as <hi>Eſa.</hi> 9.6. we cannot in that ſenſe ſay he ſhall ſit upon the ſpiritual Throne of God; for the ſpiritual Throne of God is in reference to ſpirituals: But to fit upon the Throne of <hi>David</hi> as man, will be to order it with judgement and juſtice, as is fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told of him, <hi>Eſa</hi> 9.7. yea this ſaid Throne of <hi>David</hi> which ſhall be given unto Chriſt as Mediator by his Father is ſo diſtinguiſhed by himſelf as another from his Fathers Throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21. <hi>To him that overcomes will I graunt to ſit with me on my Throne: even as I alſo overcame, and am ſet down with my Father on his Throne.</hi> Moreover the ſpiritual reign of Chriſt in the hearts of men is common to all the three Perſons in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Trinity, but to ſit upon the Throne of <hi>David</hi> as man, is peculiar to Chriſt as Mediator, as <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> God-man in one perſon; ſo the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual reign of Chriſt is one thing, but his ſitting upon the Throne of <hi>David</hi> is another; and from what hath been ſaid, they may fitly be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed in theſe reſpects following. Firſt, God the Fathers Throne and Kingdom is eternal, but Chriſts viſible glorious Kingdom as Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor is temporal, only for a ſet time, which will begin at Antichriſts de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.9, 10, 11. and at his own appearance, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. and will end when he ſhall reſign it back again to his Father, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> expreſly declares, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.24. 2dly, God the Fathets is originally in or from himſelf; but Chriſts Mediators viſible glorious Kingdom in the world is given to him of the Father, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.14. <hi>And there was given to him Dominion, Glory, and a Kingdom, that all People Nations and Languages ſhould ſerve him.</hi> Thirdly, the Throne of God the Fathers Kingdom is in Heaven, as our Saviour teacheth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21. but the Throne of his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:102111:13"/> own Kingdom as Mediator God-man ſhall in that time be on the earth, as in the text, <hi>and People Nations and Languages ſhall then ſerve him,</hi> as was laſt ſhewed, and to make it evident it muſt be done on earth: in the 27. <hi>v.</hi> of <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. it is ſaid the Kingdom and Dominion and Greatneſs of the Kingdom under the whole Heaven ſhall ſerve and obey him. Fourthly, This Temporal Kingdom for the thouſand years Chriſt will reſign back again to the Father, but his ſpiritual Kingdom as God he never received, nor will ever part from of which there will be no end. So that hence it may appear for Chriſt to reign ſpiritually in the hearts of his people as God is a thing many ways diſtinct from his ſitting upon the Throne of <hi>David</hi> as man in the time of his viſible glorious Kingdom on earth to come. Let theſe things therefore by all ſuch perſons be ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly conſidered, that they be not ſinfully found to be pleaders againſt Chriſts Intereſt in this reſpect, for which the Scripture is both clear and plentiful, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. &amp; 5.10. <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. <hi>Ier.</hi> 3.17. with many others, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> See the Forerunner, <hi>page</hi> 47, 48. and let them remember the legiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate confeſſion of Chriſt is to confeſs all things that belong to Chriſt, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogſt which, the ſitting on the Throne of <hi>David</hi> as man, will be one. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.2, 3.</p>
            <p>And as for the raiſing of the dead Saints at the Reſurrection of the Juſt as it is called, <hi>Luke</hi> 14.14. or the bleſſed firſt Reſurrection above a thouſand years before the reſt of the dead ſhall be raiſed, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.5. they being ſuch as will be counted worthy of that world (called the world to come, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5.) where thoſe Children of the Reſurrection (as our Saviour ſpeaketh, <hi>Luke</hi> 20.35, 36.) ſhall be as the Angels in Heaven, ſince at his appearance and coming into the world Chriſt will bring his Saints with him, and ſuch as ſleep in Jeſus with him, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. <hi>ult</hi> &amp; 4.14. <hi>Zac.</hi> 14.5. to the end that being raiſed from the dead he may reward them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.11. &amp; 22.12. or recompence them at the ſaid Reſurrection of the Juſt, <hi>Luke</hi> 14. when they ſhall behold the glory of Chriſt which the Father hath given him as Mediator, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.24. when his Diſciples ſhall ſit upon twelve Thrones judgeing the twelve Tribes of <hi>Iſrael, Luke</hi> 22.30. and his faithful ſervants according to the improvement of their Talents ſhall rule over ſo many Cities, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.17.19. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49.14. and ſhall have power over the Nations, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.26. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> their bodies being then redeemed from the priſon and Corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the grave, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.23. and their former mortal bodies ſhall then be powerfully raiſed by the ſame ſpirit of him that raiſed up Chriſt from the dead, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11. that ſo (then) ſuch as ſuffer for Chriſt in the body, may reign with Chriſt in his Mediators Kingdom in their bodies, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. and thoſe raiſed bodies when he ſhall appear being like him, ſhall ſee him as he is, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.2. when the Tabernacle of God ſhall be with
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:102111:13"/> men, and he be with them in the new <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> come down from God out of Heaven, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.3.10. in that City whoſe name ſhall be <hi>Iehovah Shamma</hi> the Lord is there, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 40. <hi>ult.</hi> and which ſhall then be called the Throne of of the Lord, as in the text; that City prepared for the faithful fore-fathers, yet ſo as without the faithful that died ſince Chriſts firſt to his ſecond coming they ſhall not be made perfect, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.40. or perfect in one (as our Saviour prayed, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.23.) and declares his will in the preſence of his Father, and before his Diſciples, that ſuch as were given him ſhould then be with him to behold his glory which his Father had given him, <hi>v.</hi> 24. who will then be that ſpiritual and myſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Bride, the Lambs Wife, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.9. in the time of his thouſand years reign, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. when (as ſaith the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi>) Chriſt muſt reign till he hath put all his enemies under his feet, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.25. even till he deliver up the Kingdom to God the Father; having put down all rule and all authority and power, that ſtood in his way, as in the <hi>verſe</hi> before, the laſt enemy Death being deſtroyed, <hi>v.</hi> 26. Many of theſe texts of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Scripture our bleſſed Saviour by his book of <hi>Revelation</hi> hath given much evident light unto, (as whoſoever carefully compares them, and duly weighes them, with humble and faithful ſeeking the guidance of his ſpirit may hopefully find) till which time many of theſe and divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were darkly delivered, &amp; have not otherwiſe ſo clear and fit expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion given of them, as that they will be fulfilled at that time of the reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of all things, when the times of refreſhing ſhall come, for his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from the preſence of the Lord, when God will ſend Jeſus, whom the Heavens muſt contain till then, <hi>Acts</hi> 3.19, 20, 21. in which times the many great things are to be accompliſhed which we formerly ſet down on <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. and Chriſts explication of them will at laſt be moſt certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly found the beſt; and the mean time let it be obſerved that the Doctrine of the Reſurrection was a long time but darkly ſet down in Scripture, and but by degrees were the myſteries thereof revealed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.51, 52. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.11. [as we have elſe where obſerved] and as Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> ſaith that the Prophets in the old Teſtament except <hi>Daniel,</hi> ſpake darkly or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuouſly of the firſt and ſecond coming of Chriſt, ſo we may ſay of the whole Scriptures ſpeaking of the firſt and ſecond bodily Reſurrections, till Chriſt explained them, and chiefly in <hi>Rom.</hi> 20. yet by the guidance of that, many others fall in with it. See more in the Appendix, after the Irenicon page 97. to 109. for I have in a manner but touched upon theſe texts of Scripture, becauſe I ſtudy brevity and have ſpoken there more largely of the firſt bodily Reſurrection; and becauſe the Scriptures car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with them ſo great evidence in their conſent one with another, and bearing witneſs in their order to the ſame truth, which ſerious Chriſtians may in their Meditations more inlarge and improve, that being rightly
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:102111:14"/> from the word informed of theſe things, and the like, they may both frame their prayers, &amp; make other improvements thereof accordingly, to help forwards Gods work in the fulfilling of ſome of them, having ſuch ſure and comfortable foundations from the Word, to raiſe up their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to ſuch purpoſe; and eſpecially in thoſe latter dayes when their fulfilling approacheth near, as may be obſerved from the ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling of ſo many Propheſies already; and for the accompliſhing of thoſe that remain, tends in a ſpecial manner that prayer at the end of theſe Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, with an (even ſo) as if it had been ſaid, that theſe great things in the ſaid thouſand years of Chriſts reign may be fulfilled, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.20. <hi>Even ſo. Come Lord Jeſus.</hi> And that happy eſtate of Chriſts Church in that time of his ſaid reign upon earth, ſeems to be the main drift and ſcope of the three firſt petitions of the Lords Prayer: which will then have their greateſt fulfilling on earth (as they are now fulfilled in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven) when Satan ſhall be bound and ſealed up in the bottomleſs pit, from deceiving the Nations for that thouſand years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. and wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men deſtroyed, that deſtroyed the earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18. the bleſſed and holy Saints raiſed from the dead at the firſt reſurrection, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. and the holy Angels be Chriſts attendants in Chriſts Kingdom, as the Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers of their moſt glorious King, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97. where alſo his ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible coming into the world (then) is decyphered eminently; with the joy of his people thereupon; and that which will make it an Heaven indeed, will be the Tabernacle of God will then be with men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and the Lamb will be the viſible light of that City, and the living wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of divine grace will flow ſo abundantly from the Throne of God and the Lamb, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with many other heavenly excellencies of that ſtate, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. &amp; 22. but that this may yet further appear to be then on earth; all other inferiour Creatures muſt then alſo do their homage to their hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly King, by bowing the knee, or yeilding their ſubjection to him, whoſe name is above every name; for as thoſe in heaven do it, ſo ſhall thoſe in earth and under the earth in their due time do it, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.9, 10. and ſo in ſuch a glorious condition will thoſe new Heavens and new Earth then be, that his Name will be ſanctifyed, his Kingdom will be come, and his Will (then) be done on earth, as it was (before) in heaven: [For Chriſt when he was upon earth taught not his Servants to pray all along to his coming, for thoſe things which ſhall never be; and God hath not made ſo many promiſes, and given forth ſo many propheſies of ſuch things as never will be performed and fulfilled] But then will be that great Sabbatiſme of ſuch holy refreſhment from the preſence of the Lord, and reſt which remains (ſaith the Apoſtle) for the people of God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4 9. when thoſe promiſed mercies to the Fathers ſhall be fulfilled on earth, that his people may ſerve him without fear of their enemies in holineſs
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:102111:14"/> and righteouſneſs before him all the dayes of their Life, <hi>Luke</hi> 1.73, 74. and as <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.3. now theſe promiſed mercies were to <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> not yet fulfilled, but ſeen a far off, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> There are alſo ſure mercies of <hi>David</hi> not yet fully accompliſhed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.15, 16, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that his Houſe and his Kingdom ſhould be eſtab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſhed for ever before him, and his Throne ſhall be eſtabliſhed for ever: which he there largely by Faith applyed, and by grateful acknowledgement praiſed God for, as if it had been performed; and then <hi>Job</hi> and <hi>Eſay</hi> will find the effect and fruit of their own Faith, <hi>Job</hi> 14. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 46. and <hi>Daniel</hi> ſhall then obtain his promiſed Lot, with all the holy Prophets, and faithful ſervants of God in thoſe times. Oh how ſhould our Faith be exerciſed in theſe things! that with faithful <hi>Abraham</hi> we may rejoyce aforehand, at the day of Chriſts viſible Dominion, as he did both at that, and his Incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.13, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo we ſhould proceed to a ſecond Uſe of thankfulneſs for ſuch great mercies now manifeſt to the Church of Chriſt from his Word, and chiefly from him the faithful and true witneſs; but becauſe we have been ſomwhat large to that purpoſe upon a like occaſion towards the end of a former Treatiſe on <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. we here wave that, and only touch upon ſome hints of further improvement by way of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, and exhortation, and ſo leave them to be enlarged by Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans in their private meditations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 2. For admonition to two ſorts of perſons. Firſt, to ſuch as own theſe Doctrines of Chriſts Kingdom of viſible power to come, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſo much the more to be careful to make ſure their intereſt firſt in Chriſts ſpiritual Kingdom of grace here in this preſent life, and ſtate of things, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they look or hope for any part in his Kingd. of viſible power on earth at his coming, or in Gods eternal Kingdom of glory enſuing upon it, for grace and Gods ſpirit here is the earneſt and evidence of all bleſſedneſs hereafter; only Wiſe Virgins will be admitted into the Bride-chamber, when the Bridegroom comes, and ſuch only will he receive to himſelf to make them inheritors of everlaſting bleſſedneſs in the Kingdom of his Father: for though all divine Scripture truth is written for our learning (as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth) yet all divine knowledge not being du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly improved will aggravate the ſin and miſery of all formal profeſſors thereof, both in the whole of Chriſtian religion, or in any remarkable branch thereof, much more if ſuch knowledge be perverted contrarie to the holy juſt and good laws of Chriſts Kingdom of grace, that teacheth his people to deny ungodly and worldly luſts, and to live ſoberly, righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſly &amp; Godly in this preſent world, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.11, 12. But for ſuch as own theſe Doctrines, &amp; are indeed faithful ſervants, and ſubjects of their great Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt, to look upon all Doctrine reſpecting
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:102111:15"/> Chriſts Kingdom on earth, as a great ingagement unto duty and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs, not only in word and outward profeſſion, but moſt eſpecially to endeavour to manifeſt it in heart and converſation, buth before him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and in the ſight of men, and that they may ſo labour the more to act thankfulneſs by walking ſo much the more Chriſtianly and obedient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to his Laws, ſeeing by ſuch Doctrine a greater engagement is laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them thereunto: for as their expectations are greater than otherwiſe they could be, from the evidence they have of their intereſt in Chriſts glorious Kingdom of power on earth to come, by the redemption of their bodies, and the union of them to their ſouls, in that bleſſed conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on appointed to the faithful in their order: beſides what others ſhall enjoy, who then remain in their natural life, that upon that account they ſtudy and labour to be more ready and forward to do ſuch accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſervice for Chriſt as he aſſignes them unto, though unpleaſing to fleſh and blood, becauſe it will be acceptable unto him, and he requires it of them; and it will be found no loſs [as ſome miſapprehend] but oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of great rejoycing, for thoſe ſpirits of juſt men made perfect to be brought with Chriſt at his appearance and his Kingdom, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. to attain to that deſired Union with their bodies, there to behold Chriſts glorie, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in that bleſſed condition, above a thouſand years ſooner, than the laſt reſurrection, as was manifeſt by that great exultation of the Repreſentatives, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10. as an addition to their ſpiritual joy, and praiſe to the Lamb: And (ſay they) we ſhall reign upon earth, where they knew aforehand, that they ſhould perſonally enjoy in body and ſoul the bleſſed viſion of Chriſt, and all ſuch happineſs as is appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for them in his viſible Mediators Kingdom of power upon earth; who will then be ſo admired of all his Saints, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth, and glorifyed in them that believe, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe</hi> 3. For Admonition to all real and faithful Chriſtians that as yet own not theſe Doctrines of the Millennium [which I confeſs, till of late years I my ſelf have often oppoſed, as I ſhewed in the Irenicon] to take heed and beware of ſlighting and over-looking ſo much divine truth as the fore-named, and many other texts and portions of holy Scripture hold forth evidently concerning thoſe things; and to that end conſider, firſt, ſome truths of that nature have been antiently received; though the great Deceiver then ſtirred up ſome to caſt unjuſt reproaches, and falſe imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions upon the owners of them; yea they have been owned both by anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Fathers, and modern writers, and the light and evidence of them is like to break forth more and more amongſt faithful Chriſtians, as preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dices are removed, and more Myſteries are accompliſhed, and (by Gods mercy) greater diſcoveries made of what concerns his true Church: and if diligent and impartial ſearch were made of thoſe Scriptures which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:102111:15"/> theſe things, but eſpecially what <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaks concerning the 4th or <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchie, according to the judgement of divers learned men, and that firſt more generally, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2. &amp; <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Med<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Dr. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> Mr. <hi>S.</hi> cala. menſ. <hi>c.</hi> 16. <hi>p.</hi> 183.</note> or more particularly of the riſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchie, <hi>c.</hi> 11. 18. 30. 36<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and then of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and ſtate of it till Chriſts appearance, <hi>c.</hi> 12. 1. it ſeems very probable, that many perſons of the beſt ſtate and worth, may ſee cauſe to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge much thereof, and eſpecially when they ſhall find Chriſts <hi>Revelation</hi> given to his Church in theſe times of the end, is nothing but a divine my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical Comment upon the 4th Monarchie in <hi>Dan.</hi> and his own Kingdom to ſucceed it, as we have ſhewed in our Abridgement on <hi>Dan.</hi> and the paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lel enſuing it, (as we have ſet down in a direction in the Epiſtle before this parallel; and yet more in this reſpect, when they ſhall find that there is nothing of weight that hath not been anſwered ſufficiently, and ſollid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, as we ſhewed in our tract on <hi>Gen.</hi> 5.15.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe ult.</hi> To exhort all ſuch faithfull Chriſtians that own all other parts of divine Doctrine, but not theſe as yet, to take that Candle of the Lord, that he hath put into them, <hi>Prov.</hi> 20.21<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> even their own underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Soul as it is given to them from him, without prepoſſeſſion, preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, partiality, ſelf-ends or intereſts, and ſo let them ſearch into all divine Truths reſpecting theſe things, as God may give them helps and advanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges to make uſe of, yet only as grounded upon, and warranted by the written word of God: Searching therein (with the noble <hi>Bereans</hi>) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther theſe things be ſo; for it is a heinous thing to be found fighters againſt any Truth of God. But we ought to improve all we have, or are to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote divine Truth when called to it, to ſtand up for it, and witneſs to it. For as it is great folly, vanity, and ſin, to pleaſe our ſelves, with expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions from Chriſts Religion that he hath given us no ground or warrant for: So it would be as much for any Chriſtian, that would be owned of Chriſt Jeſus, willingly to neglect, or regardleſly to paſs by ſuch things as Chriſt in much graciouſneſs tenders to his Church for her encouragement and coſolation; which muſt needs prove in ſuch matters very unacceptable to him, and is like to procure to them more blame from him (when he ſhall appear) then (haply) they are aware of: Let men therefore in due ſeaſon ſeriouſly conſider theſe things, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="section">
               <head>Further directions for the uſe of all theſe Books then were ſet down in <hi>3</hi> late Epiſtles to <hi>Gen. 3.15. Jer. 3.12.</hi> and the <hi>8</hi> convincing Arguments.</head>
               <p n="1">1. FIrſt, read the 4th part with the <hi>Scheme</hi> in one ſheet, on <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. [to be placed next before <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.20. <hi>Behold, I come quickly!</hi>] wherein with <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.17. concerning the new <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> on earth to come, are contained the ſubſtance of all thoſe Goſpel Truths reſpecting Chriſts Kingdom to come.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:102111:16"/>2. And to manifeſt how fitly thoſe Doctrines agree with all other di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine truths, therewith conſider well all thoſe divine Theſes in <hi>p</hi> 9, 10, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the Prodromus or forerunner, but eſprcially obſerve the 11, 12, 13. with that refeence of <hi>Decemb.</hi> 7.46. for which ſee <hi>p.</hi> 44, 45 46. of the ſame, alſo <hi>p.</hi> 3, 4. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the <hi>Irenic.</hi> with Arg. there, and <hi>p.</hi> 33. Unto which may be added the letter of <hi>Nov.</hi> 3.36. <hi>p.</hi> 15, 16. wherein much of thoſe Truths is touched alſo.</p>
               <p n="3">3. And for an help unto the 3d part, <hi>viz.</hi> the Abridgement and Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lels <hi>Daniel,</hi> with the <hi>Revelation</hi> which is of great uſe for the foundations of ſure diſcovery of all ſuch Doctrines, diligently peruſe the Letter to Mr. <hi>Cal. May</hi> 20. 64. <hi>p.</hi> 22, 23. of the Prodr. and the Scheme of the book of <hi>Revelation</hi> concerning the times and order of the Seals, Trumpets and Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>als, in which Letter obſerve well theſe 2 diſtinctions there ſet down to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the end thereof, which will be found to be of very great concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in theſe Doctrines. Firſt, the diſtinction of the laſt myſtical Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet, or 3d woe Trumpet, when (Antichriſt being utterly deſtroyed) the Kingdoms of the world become the Kingdoms of Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. And of the laſt ſounding Trumpet, above 1000 years after, <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4 16. (for they differ in nature as well as times) when the general Rapture and glorious Change of all Sts. ſhall be, as 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15 51, 52. The other Diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on alſo in this ſame Letter greatly to be noted, is the different ſtate of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in Chriſts Kingdom. Firſt, ſome will be raiſed Sts in the firſt bleſſed Reſurrection, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.6, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> deſcribed <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 2dly, Another ſort of perſons will be in the natural life which are ſaid (then) to walk in the light of the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> called <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.24 the nations of them that ſhall be ſaved: the not obſerving of theſe two directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons evidently grounded on holy Scripture have been the ground of many mens errors, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Then compare that ſaid Letter of <hi>May</hi> 20.64. with another A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridgement of the Seal-Propheſie, and book-Propheſie in the <hi>Revelation</hi> as <hi>p.</hi> 26, 27, 28, 29. of the Irenicon or 2d part. Both which Propheſies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the orders of times from Chriſts aſcending to heaven, <hi>Acts</hi> 1. to his coming again, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.1. with 20.1, 2, 3, 4. till the good new world ſhall begin. But firſt the Seal Propheſie is of Civil matters in the <hi>Roman</hi> ſtate chiefly; and 2dly the Book-Propheſie is of the Eccleſiaſtick affairs in the true and falſe Church, and both of them until the new and good world to come ſhall begin, as <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.21. <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.20, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. Furthermore for the attaining of better light in the whole <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation,</hi> after the former Letter, read obſervantly the large paper of <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cember</hi> 7.26<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>p.</hi> 26, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of the Prodro. concerning two defects of Mr. <hi>Durhams</hi> Book of <hi>Scotland</hi> on the whole book of the <hi>Revelation</hi> with the Scheme thereof; one was his miſtaking of the times (in great part)
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:102111:16"/> for near 100 years: the other defect was his paſſing over the new <hi>Jeruſal.</hi> ſtate; and Chriſts ſaid Kingdom of power, or (as <hi>Mede</hi> on <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.35. ſtiles it) the Kingdom of the Mountain, throughout all the book of <hi>Rev.</hi> as if nothing there had been ſaid of it in this world, though the Elders, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſay expreſly, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.10. we ſhall reign upon earth: that paper will be of very good uſe, and being well obſerved with the others, giveth much light to that Book of the <hi>Revelation:</hi> and all the ſaid helps to the uſe of the Parallels in the third book or part on <hi>Dan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. As for our ſecond part, <hi>viz.</hi> the Irenicon, it is to prove ſuch a Kingdom with the late 8 Arguments in the [Word written, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring to it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>The Penmans further humble acknowledgement.</head>
               <p>MOſt Bleſſed Lord God, I thy poor weak and unworthy Servant, do in all humility of Soul by the help of thy holy Spirit through Jeſus Chriſt my Saviour, three in Perſons as formerly confeſſed by me, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  <note n="(a)" place="margin">Ser Prodr. p. 9, 10, 11, 12. &amp; Dir. 2d.</note> and now to thy praiſe, before thy Omni-preſent Divine Majeſty, and before Angels and Men, I do here alſo again confeſs and declare thy great, manifold, and free mercy (together with innumerable experiences thereof otherwiſe from my youth) that in particular thou haſt ſo manifeſted unto me through the riches of thy grace in Chriſt that glorious part of his Mediators Offices ſtill to be fulfilled, which (as I have profeſſed) ſo ſtill I eſteem to be, the greateſt mercy (ſince thy gifts of faith, grace, and thy holy ſpirit conferred upon me) that I have been capable of receiving in this life. And with humble thankfulneſs, I eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially acknowledge thy good hand towards me, and upon me, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, carrying on, and at laſt (after ſome interruption yet again turned by thy hand to good advantage) thou wert pleaſed to inable me to finiſh the four parts of the foundations of theſe truths divers years paſt, and by degrees to proceed in thoſe practicals after publiſhed.</p>
               <p>And firſt, that (a little before the Cities ſad conflagration) thou waſt pleaſed upon the ſaid advantage (as in other reſpects) ſo eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally to inable me (then) to compoſe that Piece on <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.20. from the ground of thoſe<note n="b" place="margin">Iren. <hi>p.</hi> 41, 42, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> diſtinctions of the Spiritual, Viſional, Executive, Repreſentative Comings (together with three Perſonal Comings) of my Saviour, all (as I believe) taught me remarkably (with the due uſe of other means) by thy Word and Spirit: which laſt (if it will be only in the<note n="c" place="margin">as Word written <hi>p. ult.</hi>
                  </note> apprehenſion of Creatures) yet, I believe, it is by thy Word ſaid to be his deſcending with a ſhout, and the Voice of an Arch-Angel, and with the Trump of God, above 1000 years after his ſecond Perſonal coming, as by that Scripture Evidence thou didſt inable me (then) to ſet down.</p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:102111:17"/>
               <p>And alſo, that in that order of my Saviours execution of his three great Offices ſet down in ſome of my Theſes written on a Lords-day morning, (not without the ſpecial motion and aſſiſtance of his Spirit as I conceive) I was firſt inabled to ſet down that little obſerved, yet very real and uſeful diſtinction of<note n="d" place="margin">Theſe. 11, 12, 13. of <hi>p.</hi> 10. of Prodro.</note> his general &amp; particular execution of them, as a foundation of drawing up that Treatiſe afterwards on <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. to ſet forth by Scripture and experience, how he hath, doth, and will accompliſh them all, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And Laſtly, by convincing Arguments, and other helps, (which thy Divine goodneſs hath ordered to be ſubſervient,) that thou haſt now been graciouſly pleaſed, after many divertings for divers years paſt (and to much advantage likewiſe of my work) of what I my ſelf formerly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended concerning the Tract on the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> from <hi>Jer.</hi> 3.17. yet that after the ceaſing almoſt in me any ſuch intentions or hopes thereof, thou haſt remarkably again led me in wayes to fin ſh thy own Work, ſo much the more to thy own praiſe, by how much my own weakneſs and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthineſs have rendered me unſuitable for ſuch an undertaking, had I not been both firſt prepared, then ſet apart, quickned, aſſiſted, encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, and carried on remarkably by thy Grace and good Spirit according to thy Word (as I alſo really believe) and which aſſured perſwaſion, hath made me greatly unmoveable (ſo far as I found thy Gracious hand leading me on therein) that at laſt the Top-ſtone of that main Building (is by this Tract on Jer. 3.17.) now at laſt laid thereon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> So (Father) it ſeemed good to thee, when thou hadſt before hid many of theſe things from many Wiſe and Prudent; and even in ſuch things, cauſed the fooliſh in the world to confound the wiſe: for thou art all and alone ſo, and all Creatures are nothing but by thee: to thee there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be all the praiſe from all thine for evermore, for of thee, and by thee, and for thee, are all things; and (Gracious Father) let many of thine from this thy Work (by my weak hand) be daily the more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abled to render the ſame unto thee, in regard of thy ſpecial goodneſs in theſe Divine Truths here ſet before them: which is the main and juſt intendment thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>Amen, and Amen, by me and them for Evermore.</closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>In Prodr. <hi>p.</hi> 9. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 4. add in the execution of the eternal Decrees. In the Advertiſement before the Irenic. r. ſupernal for ſupernatural, &amp; <hi>p.</hi> 100. r. Ideom for Idem. In the Word written <hi>p. ult.</hi> r. late 5t Monarchie men, and after grave for great. In the New <hi>Jeruſ. p.</hi> 12. <hi>l.</hi> 35. r. moſt for not.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:102111:17"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
